Sai Deogekar

+49 1782280620 | sai.deogekar@gmail.com | Homepage | Google Scholar | LinkedIn

SUMMARY —

Highly motivated Mechanical Engineer with 9 years of experience in Computational Solid Mechanics and 2 years of experience in technical support for Finite Element Analysis. Proficient in the use of FEA Modeling and Simulation tools, Numerical Methods and Structural Mechanics. Skilled team player experienced in the Agile Scrum Methodology with high independence in remote environments.

EDUCATION -

PhD, Mechanical Engineering

December 2019

Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (RPI), Troy, NY, USA, GPA: 3.89/4.00

Master of Science, Mechanical Engineering

August 2015

University of Cincinnati (UC), Cincinnati, OH, USA, GPA: 3.87/4.00

Bachelor of Technology, Mechanical Engineering

May 2012

Visvesvaraya National Institute of Technology (VNIT), Nagpur, India, *GPA*: 8.79/10.00

SKILLS

Modeling Tools: Ansys Mechanical, Ansys Workbench, Ansys LS-DYNA, Abaqus, Ansys SpaceClaim, CATIA **Programming Languages:** High performance computing using C, C++, FORTRAN

Scripting Languages: MATLAB, Python

General: Microsoft Suite (Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Access, Outlook), Windows OS, Linux OS, shell scripting

EXPERIENCE -

Senior Technical Support Engineer at Ansys, Inc.

Sept. 2021 - Oct. 2021

- Applied expertise of Modeling and Simulation of structural mechanics to provide technical support to customers and channel partners and ensured highest levels of customer satisfaction.
- Led projects involving partner universities and collaborated with the marketing, the course creation, and the infrastructure teams to ensure smooth and efficient deployment of high-quality technical courses.
- Proven record of taking up and solving problems that involve challenging modeling tasks and steep learning curves.

Technical Support Engineer II at Ansys, Inc.

Sept. 2019 – Sept. 2021

- Developed, created and deployed educational content that covered various topics such as stress analysis, modal analysis, thermal analysis, etc. through engaging videos and hands-on simulation models.
- Created finite element models to demonstrate various key features of the Ansys Mechanical software to train and coach new customers during online trainings and webinars.

Failure in Fibrous Materials

Aug. 2016 – Sept. 2019

PhD Thesis, RPI

- Performed nonlinear, static and dynamic finite element (FE) simulations to investigate failure mechanisms in fibrous materials such as biological tissues, paper, nonwovens, etc. and develop structure-property relationships between material strength and microstructural parameters.
- Developed a new class of fibrous materials with superior performance and longevity (25% increase in strength and toughness) by modifying the network topology to increase its inherent heterogeneity.

Characterizing the Behavior of Fibrous Materials with Nonlocal Continuum Model Oct. 2015 – Oct. 2017 Research Project, RPI (in collaboration with Université de Lorraine)

• Collaborated with a team of four people to develop a nonlocal continuum theory for material characterization of fibrous materials and to quantify the relations between mechanical properties of the effective continuum and microstructural parameters of the material.

Sai Deogekar Résumé 1/2

Multiscale Modeling of Facet Capsule Ligament (FCL)

Research Project, RPI (in collaboration with University of Pennsylvania and University of Minnesota)

• Collaborated with an interdisciplinary team of eight people to model deformation and damage in a human spine ligament (FCL), using a multiscale FEA code (written in C++). This method eliminates the need to develop constitutive material models and instead solves a sub-scale problem to get material behavior.

Research Assistant at University of Cincinnati Simulation Center

Feb. 2013 – June 2015

Dec. 2015 – Dec. 2016

Research Project in collaboration with Procter & Gamble, UC

- Worked in the Baby Care department to analyze the product performance of various components of diapers using M&S tools (Abaqus, Python). Simulated nonlinear systems with large deformations, material nonlinearity and contact, and supported development and extension of simulation programs.
- Documented the simulation results in weekly technical reports and made recommendations to guide development work.

Computational Study of Dynamic Brittle Fracture Using the Phase-field Method Dec. 2012 – June 2015 *Master's Thesis, UC*

- Implemented a mathematical model of the phase-field approach in MATLAB and in C (using SPOOLES library) to study crack propagation under dynamic loading, eliminating the need for tracking discontinuities numerically.
- Modeled branching of cracks and interaction among multiple cracks in glass and ceramic composite structures using dynamic, implicit FEM.

High Performance Implementation of 2D Laplace Solver

Oct. 2013 – Dec. 2013

2018

Research Project, UC

• Implemented and parallelized (using Message Passing Interface) an additive Schwarz method in C.

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS ———

- **Deogekar, S.**, and R. C. Picu, *Strength of Stochastic Fibrous Materials Under Multiaxial Loading*, Soft Matter, 17 (3), 704, (2021).
- **Deogekar, S.**, Z.Yan, R. C. Picu, *Random Fiber Networks with Superior Properties Through Network Topology Control*, Journal of Applied Mechanics, 86 (8), 081010, (2019).
- **Deogekar, S.**, and R. C. Picu, *On the Strength of Random Fiber Networks*, Journal of the Mechanics and Physics of Solids, 116, 1, (2018).
- Picu R. C., **S. Deogekar** and M. R. Islam, *Poisson Contraction and Fiber Kinematics in Tissue: Insight from Collagen Network Simulations*, Journal of Biomechanical Engineering, 140 (2), 021002, (2018).
- Berkache, K., S. Deogekar, I. Goda, R. C. Picu, and J. F. Ganghoffer, *Construction of Second Gradient Continuum Models for Random Fibrous Networks and Analysis of Size Effects*, Composite Structures, 181, 347, (2017).
- **Deogekar, S.**, and K. Vemaganti, A Computational Study of the Dynamic Propagation of Two Offset Cracks Using the Phase Field Method, Engineering Fracture Mechanics, 182, 303, (2017).

GRADUATE ACADEMIC COURSES –

Advanced Finite Element Method
High Performance Computing
Scientific Computing
Plasticity

Fracture Mechanics and Fatigue
Modeling of Materials
Plasticity

Advanced Solid Mechanics
Continuum Mechanics
Elasticity

ACHIEVEMENTS AND AWARDS -

• Collaboration and Teamwork Award, Ansys 2021

• Edison Award for Education (awarded to the Ansys Innovation Courses team) 2021

Materials Research Society, Oral Presentation Award, Fall Meeting

• Procter & Gamble Tuition Award 2013 – 2015

• University Graduate Scholarship, University of Cincinnati 2012 – 2015

• Fastest Car Award, Supra Society of Automotive Engineers 2011

Sai Deogekar Résumé 2/2